<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hatred of Esau, and the love of Jacob unfoulded being a brief and plain exposition of the 9. chapter of Pauls epistle to the Romanes, being the heads of what was delivered in several discourses, both publick and private. By Samuel Loveday servant of the church of Christ.</title>
            <author>Loveday, Samuel, 1619-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88607</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1380_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209387</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868267</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868267</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169893</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88607)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169893)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 180:E1380[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hatred of Esau, and the love of Jacob unfoulded being a brief and plain exposition of the 9. chapter of Pauls epistle to the Romanes, being the heads of what was delivered in several discourses, both publick and private. By Samuel Loveday servant of the church of Christ.</title>
                  <author>Loveday, Samuel, 1619-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Clowes, for Gieles Calvert, at the black Spread-Eagle, at the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1650].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 27. 1650".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans IX --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169893:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The hatred OF ESAU, And the Love of JACOB un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foulded, being a <hi>Brief</hi> and plain Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the 9. Chapter of <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> being the heads of what was delivered in ſeveral diſcourſes, both Publick and private.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Loveday</hi> Servant of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <bibl>
                  <hi>Jud.</hi> 4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Qui reddet cuique ſecundum opera ejus,</hi> 
               <bibl>Rom. 2.6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Credens &amp; baptizatus ſalvabitur: at non cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens Condemnabitur.</hi> 
               <bibl>Marc. 16.16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by <hi>John Clowes,</hi> for <hi>Gieles Calvert,</hi> at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Spread-hagle, at the weſt-end of Pauls.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169893:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169893:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been ſeated in the heart of man (ſince the fall of Adam) to put off the ſin from himſelf and put it upon others, yea, upon God himſelf. Although it is very ſtrange that man can find none to Father his corruptions upon but upon him that is purity it ſelf, who as James ſpeaks, <hi>James</hi> the firſt, and the thirteenth, cannot be tempted with evil, neither tempteth he any man. The Woman that thou gaveſt me (ſaith Adam,) <hi>Geneſis</hi> the third and the twelfth, gave me, and I did eat, man is very loath to lay the ſaddle upon the right horſe, as I may ſo ſay, he is
<pb facs="tcp:169893:3"/>loath to take it upon himſelf, the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which thou gaveſt me. Old Adam in theſe words laid a platform to all his ſons, to ſay as their Father ſaid, the want of ſtrength from the cauſe, he not being over-powered by thee, he not being compelled by thee, thy determination and appointing me is the cauſe that I am as I am, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt made me thus. But let us a little conſider what harm God did to Adam in giving him this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, could not Adam have made uſe of her to no other end? nay, did not God give him her to do her good, and not hurt, <hi>Proverbs</hi> the 31. and the 12. Thus I ſay miſapplying and miſappro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Gods dealings in Judgements or mercies, that makes men loſers; here is <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart hardned by God even by giving him deliverances: if you take good notice of it, its not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the plagues, but under the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances, as you ſhall finde in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb facs="tcp:169893:3"/>diſcourſe, becauſe man is ſo bad himſelf, therefore he judgeth God to be like him, as in the 50 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> the 21. to reap where he hath not ſtrowed, as <hi>Luke</hi> the 19 and 11. though indeed few men deal ſo hardly with their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, but I pray conſider the Judge of all the earth ſhall do right, that is to render to every man according to his works, <hi>Romanes</hi> the 2. and whatſoever he exhorteth man unto, be aſſured, he is not failing in himſelf.</p>
            <p>Therefore read without prejudice, and weigh things ſeriouſly, and ſee if theſe things be ſo, and ſee what wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms children ſpeak, thoſe that are begotten by wiſdom which is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> for wiſdom their Father is ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by them, <hi>Luke</hi> 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> 35. and take good notice of the 29 <hi>verſ.</hi> of the ſame <hi>Chapter,</hi> the Publicanes juſtified God, being baptized with the baptiſme of <hi>John.</hi> Know this that God is moſt juſt and equal in his proceedings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:169893:4"/>the ſons of men, my deſire is that this labour of mine may be to thy profit whomſoever thou art, and if thou reapeſt benefit let God have the praiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169893:4"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle Dedicatory <hi>To his Honoured Father</hi> WILLIAM LOVEDAY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ear Father, becauſe this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing diſcourſe wants an Indulgent Reader, therefore I thought good to preſent it firſt to your hands, hoping you will readily paſs by thoſe failings which may appear therein, and cloath them with your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable conſtruction and Fatherly love, and look further then the ſhell, even to the kernell and marrow of this buſineſs, I ſhall not preſent it to you as a free gift, but as my obliged duty, as a ſmall part of requital for your Inceſſant love. I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to conſider ſeriouſly of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and not to undervalue it, becauſe of the meanneſs of the Author; but know I pray you that Gods way and courſe in the dayes of the Goſpel is to appear in weak means to advance his own glory, that no
<pb facs="tcp:169893:5"/>fleſh may glorie in his preſence: Out of the mouths of babes and ſucklings, he will perfect his praiſe; and not onely ſo, but he will lay low the wiſdom of the World, and the pride of men who ſtumble at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe he is ſo obſcure in the World that they cannot ſee him, neither will they ſtoop ſo low as to take notice of him; but I hope better things of you, therefore accept this ſmall fruit from me, and what benefit you receive I doubt not but you will be ready to give God the praiſe. So fare-well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169893:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Brief expoſition upon the ninth chap. of the</hi> Rom.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Say the truth in <hi>Chriſt</hi> I lie not, my conſcience bearing me witneſſe in the holy Spirit, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the former Chapters of this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle largely treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the glorious and happy condition of thoſe that were entered into the way of the Goſpel; in oppoſition to the Law, calling it being in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. Which being in <hi>Chriſt</hi> is to be in and under the Ordinances of the Goſpel, as <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>chap. verſ.</hi> 27.</p>
            <p>As many of you as are baptized into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> have put on <hi>Chriſt.</hi> In the two former verſes it is called Faith, in oppoſition to works. The way of the Goſpel is called Faith, <hi>chap.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:169893:6"/>My little children of whom I travel in birth, untill <hi>Chriſt</hi> be formed in you, (which is) till you worſhip according to the Goſpel: and not according to the Law, as in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing verſes.</p>
            <p>So that being in <hi>Chriſt</hi> according to the firſt verſe of the 8. chap. Is to walk in, and under the Ordinances of the Goſpel. It is likewiſe called Spirit, in oppoſition to fleſh, as this Epiſtle treateth of, as alſo the Epiſtle to the <hi>Gal. chap.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. he that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the Spirit, (that is) he that was born of works, or of the Law, perſecuted him that was born according to Faith.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle having (I ſay) again largely expounded and Amplified thoſe two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, <hi>(viz.)</hi> works and Faith, in the ſeventh and eight chap. ſhewing in the latter end of the eight, what cauſe he and the reſt of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Saints (believers in <hi>Chriſt</hi>) had to Triumph in, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 34.</p>
            <p>Nothing ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God in <hi>Chriſt:</hi> (that is) ſtill in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Law, for under the Law there were many ſeparations from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (as I may ſo call them) upon which ſo many ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices were required to bring them together
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169893:6"/>again, but now <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath by that one Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of his, for ever conſecrated thoſe that are ſanctified, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>I would not here be miſtaken, as though men thus ſanctified could not again be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, for then I ſhould contradict other Scriptures, as the ſecond of <hi>Peter,</hi> the 2 <hi>chap.</hi> from the twentieth verſe to the end, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Scriptures. But thus, under the Law let a man do what he could to keep himſelf pure, yet there would be defilements, and ſo ſeparations from God and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but now God doth not ſo require purity of men, (that is) external purity, (that is) to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from touching of dead bodies or the like, but now onely wilfull ſins make a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration betwixt God and man, (I mean) thoſe once truly joined unto him, ſee <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. If we ſin wilfully after we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the knowledge of the truth, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains no more ſacrifice for ſins.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle (I ſay,) being thus very high in his expreſſions of his bleſſed condition, with the reſt of the Saints, <hi>(viz.)</hi> believers in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as verſe the firſt, he now like an affectionate friend looks back upon the reſt of his kindred after the fleſh, as it is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a compaſſionate heart, to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169893:7"/>others as well as himſelf, and to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to bring others to the ſame enjoyment with himſelf, this was <hi>Pauls</hi> condition, as if he ſhould ſay: Am I and you who are in <hi>Chriſt</hi> thus happy &amp; glorious? But ſtay, have none loſt that which we have found? yes, you my brethren the Jews have loſt that which we have found: therefore my joy is a little abated; this he is now upon, he doth not onely hug and embrace the thing found, but withall he wiſheth he could perſwade the owners to take it of him again, though he loſe it, ſee verſe the third, where the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle wiſhes himſelf accurſed, or ſeparated from <hi>Chriſt</hi> for his brethren his kinſmen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh.</p>
            <p>Therefore the diſcourſe that follows, is to be looked upon as from a man deeply ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his friends loſſe, which will cauſe him to comfort himſelf, and them with this, that the loſt goods ſhall be returned. Now I come to the words, verſe the 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1. I ſay the truth in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I lie not, my conſcience alſo bearing me witneſſe in the holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>Theſe words are a preface to that which follows: the words themſelves are an affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; or I may ſay an oath, where the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169893:7"/>Apoſtle doth affirm that he will ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but truth in this following diſcourſe: and therefore according to the cuſtome of men he ſwears himſelf, being not required by any other.</p>
            <p>We have in the words ſomething to be underſtood, or explained, as what he means by ſaying the truth in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Secondly, what he means by not lying, or by a lie. Thirdly, what he means by Conſcience. Fourthly, what he means by holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, to wit ſpeaking the truth in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I underſtand he meaneth, that he will not preſent that before them, which is not (which we call a lie,) but ſpeak words in reference to <hi>Chriſt</hi> who is truth it ſelf, and ſpeak them as the truth it ſelf, and ſpeak them as the truth is in <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and ſo it being truth which he ſhould ſpeak, it muſt center in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is the truth it ſelf.</p>
            <p>But the ſecond will more explain it, what he means by a lie.</p>
            <p>The Greeck word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is ſeverally ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the Scriptures, ſometimes it is taken for vanity or emptineſſe, in oppoſition to ſubſtance and fulneſſe, ſo God is ſaid to be true and every man a liar, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>chap. verſ.</hi> 4. And ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> was ſaid to be full of grace
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169893:8"/>and truth, <hi>John</hi> the 1. <hi>chap. verſ.</hi> 4. And ſo God will be worſhipped in Spirit and truth. <hi>John</hi> the 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. But this lie is in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to truth, and ſo Idols are called a lie, in oppoſition to this ſubſtance <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> ſee <hi>Eſai.</hi> 44. <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. Speaking of Idols he ſaith, is not there a lie in my right hand, and ſo the Devill is called a liar, becauſe be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades men to that which is not, as at the firſt he did to Eve, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3. <hi>chap. verſ.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Apoſtle exhorts the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and ſo conſequently all believers in Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order to put away lying, ſee <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, for that word conſcience, the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which hath affinity with the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and underſtanding with the mind, and regard with the affections, as <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 48. <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. the words of <hi>Jacob,</hi> I know well my Son, I know well, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> the 8. Who knew not Joſeph, that is he did not know him ſo as to regard him, ſo <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 49.11. Where the ſame word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is here rendred con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, is rendred an inward thought, ſee likewiſe <hi>Luke</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. <hi>Math.</hi> 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. Where the Lord is ſaid not to know the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169893:8"/>workers of iniquity, that is, not to know them ſo, as to regard them with his inward affections, ſo that now the Apoſtle will ſpeak nothing but what he knows very well, and is affected with.</p>
            <p>Fourthly what he means by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the holy ſpirit, by which we are to underſtand, ſometimes that viſible diſcovery of cloven tongues, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.3. ſometimes a Dove, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. ſometimes for the word of <hi>Chriſt</hi> as <hi>John</hi> the 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. Compared with 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. Where you may ſee that that which is called Spirit in the one place is called word in another; ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. The Spirit of God beares wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with our Spirits that we are the Sons of God, to wit, the word: this is that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which being received, and believed quickneth, ſee <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119. <hi>verſ.</hi> 50. Where <hi>David</hi> ſaith thy word hath quickned me. Compare this with the 6. of <hi>John,</hi> and the 63. Which will make it appear plainly, that the word is that quickning Spirit: ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith in the concluſion of the verſe, The words that I ſpeak, they are Spirit and life; and ſo our bodies are ſaid to be a habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for God by his Spirit, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. compared with <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. Let the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169893:9"/>word of <hi>Chriſt</hi> dwell richly in you: and to this add, 1. <hi>John</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. Let that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore abide in you which you have heard from the beginning, which if it do, ye ſhall continue in the Father and in the Son: to this add <hi>John</hi> 15. <hi>verſ</hi> 7. If ye abide in me, and my words abide in you, ye ſhall ask what you will, and it ſhall be done unto you: this is that Spirit or anointing, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> which makes us on with God, as we have the mind of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or Spirit of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſee 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. That is as we have the word of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſpeak the more of this, becauſe men in theſe late dayes ſpeak much of a Spirit, and yet lay low the words of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which are Spirit and life: but take notice, this is that Spirit, that doth cleanſe, comfort, exhort, and lead into truth, yea, and make the man of God perfect and wiſe unto ſalvation, ſee 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 15.17.</p>
            <p>The word Spirit, if we take it, as it is taken for the quinteſſence or abſtract of God, as it may be ſo called, for it brings us thus to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of God: God at the firſt was (to us) an incomprehenſible being, therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> could not deal with God as he was to be looked upon, but deſires God to ſpeak in a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169893:9"/>way more ſuitable to him, which was by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them Laws to walk by, which God did for him and the reſt, ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this ſpeaking of God was too hard to be underſtood, (that is,) what his intent was in thoſe ſacrifices and ceremonies wherein he was darkly ſeen, this was the firſt degree of Gods condeſcenſion to man, to be abſtracted, (as I may ſo ſay) and here was ſpirit abſtracted from God, that ſo by a little, man might underſtand and taſte, what this vaſte incomprehenſible being was: but this was not all, but God therefore is pleaſed further to be abſtracted, that is, to ſend <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is more expreſly his image: now this Spirit comes to be more ſtrong, and gives a nearer diſcovery what this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible being is: but this is not all neither, but this Image, or Abſtract, or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, muſt yet again be diſtilled through the Limbick or Stil of ſufferings; and death it ſelfe, to bring forth yet a more exact Spirit: this is intimated by <hi>John</hi> 7.39. &amp; thus I have brought you down to the word of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or Mind of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is the beſt diſcovery of God, and trueſt taſte of him, that hath been yet made known unto the ſons of men.</p>
            <p>This is that Spirit ſpoken of by <hi>Chriſt,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169893:10"/>John</hi> 14.26. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.13. <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.8. which ſome taſted deeply of after <hi>Chriſts</hi> aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 3. and all taſte of, who taſte of the Word of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Goſpel of our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed there are ſome that with thoſe in the <hi>Acts</hi> 19. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. who have not received the holy Spirit ſince they believed, (that is) they have not been transformed into the ſame image of life and power. See <hi>Luke</hi> 24 49. compared with 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8. <hi>But we all beholding as in a glaſſe, the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame image, from glory to glory, even as by the Spirit (or Power) of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But are ſuch as <hi>Timothy</hi> ſpeaks of 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. <hi>who have a form of godlineſſe, but deny the power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſhews the Power of the Word or Spirit, that it is of a transforming nature; this is attributed to the Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. <hi>It is the Power of God to ſalvation to every one that believeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that Spirit or Power that <hi>Stephen</hi> was qualified withall. See <hi>Acts</hi> 7. he was full of the holy Spirit, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Our Goſpell came not unto you in word only, but alſo in power, and in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.20. <hi>The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169893:10"/>of God is not in word only, but alſo in power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that Spirit or Power which the Lord hath promiſed, and which we are to expect and pray for, according to that in <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. compared with <hi>Judges</hi> 16.28. where <hi>Sampſon</hi> prayeth for ſtrength, which in the former <hi>Chapter,</hi> 14. <hi>verſe</hi> he cals <hi>the Spirit of the Lord.</hi> Likewiſe ſee and conſider <hi>Micah</hi> 3.8.</p>
            <p>This I ſay is that Spirit which we are to taſte God by, to know God by, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend God by, namely his Word: and he that hath this Spirit dwelling or abiding in him, walketh as <hi>Chriſt</hi> walked, pleaſing to God, and profitable to men.</p>
            <p>So then thus I will ſpeak, that which I am deeply affected with, and ſhall be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall and true, not in word only, but in power. So much for the explication of the firſt <hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſe</hi> 2. <hi>That I have great heavineſſe, and continual ſorrowing of heart:</hi> This is part of that which he affirms in the former words.</p>
            <p>There are three gradations, or degrees, uſed by the Apoſtle to ſet it forth, as firſt, heavineſſe. Secondly, ſorrow, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually. We ſhall a little conſider what he means by heavineſſe and ſorrow, and what
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169893:11"/>difference there is between them, the <hi>Greek</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth heavineſſe, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſleep, as <hi>Luke</hi> 22.45. <hi>Chriſt</hi> cometh to his diſciples, and findeth them aſleep with heavineſſe: the Latin word <hi>aegritudo</hi> is taken for griefe, paſſion, or ſorrow of mind, and ſometime ſickneſſe of body, as in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. the reading theſe Scriptures following will informe you what manner of heavineſſe it was, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.6.22. it is there taken for ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. it is there taken for griefe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.27. there the ſame word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for ſorrow again, but the ſecond word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is deep, as the Latine word <hi>cruciatus,</hi> which implies torment, pain, affliction, a croſſe, and to be nailed upon a croſſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.24.</p>
            <p>It is further taken for the travel of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.3. where the ſame word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is rendred travell: ſo likewiſe <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19. it is taken for the ſorrows of death, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.24. where the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is uſed, ſo that by theſe places here cited, it appears to be very great ſorrow, even to pain and travell, nay, to be crucified for his friends the <hi>Iews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh then I might a little preſſe this upon you, is it ſo with you that profeſſe your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169893:11"/>to be of <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit: are you grieved even to death, even to crucifying, for your friends according to the fleſh, becauſe they are in darkneſſe, and do not enjoy the light of the Goſpel, which you do? I fear, we may all put our hands upon our mouths, and accuſe our ſelves of neglect of our duty in this particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> condition was like <hi>Chriſts,</hi> indeed he walked as <hi>Chriſt</hi> walked, his ſoul was ſorrowfull even unto death, even ſo was <hi>Pauls:</hi> He, who thought it no robbery to be equall with God, yet made himſelfe of no reputation, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. and was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the glory which he was before inveſted with, and was accurſed from God, which ſeparation makes him cry out, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me? Mat.</hi> 27.46. even ſo, <hi>Paul</hi> wiſheth himſelf accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or ſeparated from <hi>Chriſt</hi> for the <hi>Iews,</hi> ſuch was his love towards them, as you ſhall hear more at large when we come to the 3. <hi>v.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if we were in this condition, oh, what means would we uſe, what induſtry vvould vve uſe to be delivered, as the ſame Apoſtle expreſſes to the <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19. <hi>My little children, of whom I travel in birth, until Chriſt be formed in you:</hi> and do but look back upon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169893:12"/>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, vvhat means he uſeth from this travel, as his earneſt prayers to God for them, <hi>chap.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. ſo vvould vve, if vve vvere as <hi>Paul,</hi> how vvould vve pray in their behalfe, vvho are in darkneſſe? and not only ſo, but he uſeth means, as in the 11. of the <hi>Romans ver.</hi> 14. he there magnified his office before the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to ſee if he by any means could provoke the <hi>Jews</hi> to emulation, that thereby he might ſave ſome of them, he u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all means poſſible to bring them in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to what they loſt: and the ground is, becauſe <hi>he is in travel for them;</hi> and how vvilling a mother is to ſee her child brought forth, I leave you to judge.</p>
            <p>Neither is this a ſuddain paſſion of griefe, and ſo rejoyce again, no; and that brings me to the third aggravation here in the words; and that is, continuances, without intermiſſion: there is no time when <hi>Paul</hi> doth not bear in mind the <hi>Jews</hi> loſſe their regaining.</p>
            <p>Now then let us look back upon what hath been ſaid; he might well affirm it with ſuch ſtrong affirmations and witneſſe, it would ſcarcely have been believed elſe that he could have been ſo troubled for them; <hi>Paul</hi> was like a bird flying up into the air,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169893:12"/>in the <hi>chap.</hi> but this clog puls him down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he cannot be elevated truly (nor no Saint) till this be removed.</p>
            <p>We who are Saints ſhould look upon our ſelves as tied to theſe dead carcaſes (I mean the <hi>Jews</hi>) we cannot be right as we would be till they have life in them, no aſcending with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, no triumphing without them, ſo <hi>Paul</hi> hath it <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.15. <hi>Their reſtoring ſhall be life from the dead, when they and we ſhall be one body:</hi> as in another caſe it is ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.48. <hi>That the Saints that are gone before with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) ſhould not be made perfect;</hi> ſo neither they nor we vvithout them ſhall be made perfect.</p>
            <p>Therefore what need have we to be in <hi>Pauls</hi> frame; me thinks, it is like a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny travelling towards a City, and ſome fall by the way, or ſtray behind, and the other that are willing to enter, runs forward, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding there are orders given out, that none ſhall enter until all come up together.</p>
            <p>How then ſhould this make thoſe that are ſtrong help thoſe that are weak, that they may all enter together to the gate. So let us know that none of us ſhall enter into glory, untill the <hi>Jews</hi> come up too; therefore let us uſe all means poſſible to publiſh that light,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169893:13"/>and put forth that power we have to bring them up. And ſo much for the ſecond <hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſe</hi> 3. <hi>For I could wiſh my ſelfe to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed from Chriſt for my brethren, my kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred after the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the underſtanding of theſe words, we are to conſider what is meant by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. It is taken from an <hi>Hebrew</hi> root, which ſignifies to limit, determine, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.41. <hi>They limitted the holy One of Iſrael:</hi> and the <hi>Greek</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not differing, ſignifieth to ſix, determine, or appoint; theſe words are a fruit or effect of the former: you may remember, I told you concerning his heavineſſe and ſorrow, the greatneſs of it; I told you he was brought up to the condition of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented for our ſakes to be ſeparated from the Father, as it appears by his expreſſions: See <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.46.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Paul</hi> (as I told you before) being deeply ſenſible of their loſſe, is come up to the height of his affection, but how may we underſtand this, that he deſires to be accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from <hi>Chriſt:</hi> we muſt thus take it: That <hi>Paul</hi> prefers a generall good before a particular, therefore he could wiſh himſelfe in their condition, if ſo be, they might be in his.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:169893:13"/>Now vve are not here to think, that he meaneth to be for ever ſeparated from <hi>Chriſt:</hi> for the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves his kindred are not ſo ſeparated; for all acknowledge that they ſhall come in again, onely he deſires that if it were poſſible they might have been firſt, though he were laſt, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Iews, The firſt ſhall be laſt, and the laſt firſt,</hi> ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.30. that is, <hi>The Iews who were firſt a people, for their rebellion againſt God, ſhall be laſt, and the Gentiles who were not a people, ſhall be firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is another acception of this word, (that is) <hi>to be blotted out of the book of life:</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> uſeth the ſame expreſſions to <hi>God,</hi> ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.32. <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.15. which agrees with that (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.24. which is excommunicated to death, as it is ſometimes taken, but I take it to be the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, (that is to ſay) that <hi>Paul</hi> deſires (for a time) to be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the room of the <hi>Iews,</hi> who were ſo excommunicated for their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience.</p>
            <p>Then if it be ſo, let us a little conſider, (as I ſaid before) <hi>Paul</hi> might well affirm it with ſuch ſtrong affirmations; for it might have been ſcarcely believed that his love and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169893:14"/>affection, ſhould be ſo ſtrong towards the <hi>Jews:</hi> where ſhall we find ſuch love? here is ſuch love, as <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of, to lay down our lives for the brethren, here was that love of <hi>Chriſt</hi> viſibly ſeen in <hi>Paul,</hi> which we are commanded to imitate.</p>
            <p>It is no wonder, though <hi>Paul</hi> writes ſo tenderly to the Churches, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1. <hi>chap.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. I write to you as my beloved children, I have begotten you, and ſo the whole currant of his Epiſtles was full of loving expreſſions, as a tender Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Who would have thought, that ever that <hi>Saul</hi> ſpoken of <hi>Acts</hi> 8. Who you there read did make havock of the Churches, drawing out Men and Woman, putting them into priſon, he breathed out threatnings againſt the people of God: his very name implies a man of a turbulent Spirit, a deſperate, forcing, or Raping man: but ſee what power he hath met withal in the commands of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that his Name is not onely changed, but his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alſo, for <hi>Paul</hi> ſignifies (<hi>ſeparavit</hi>) that is, ſet apart.</p>
            <p>We may plainly ſee the power of the Word, of what a transforming nature it is, it transformed a man into love, not onely to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169893:14"/>his brethren, but alſo to his enemies: This Doctrine <hi>Chriſt</hi> preacheth largely, ſee and conſider <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 43.44. It hath been ſaid, love your Neighbours; but I ſay love your Enemies: do good to them that hate you, and bleſſe them that curſe you: and theſe words of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> muſt be transforming words, to thoſe that profeſſe themſelves to be Diſciples of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This leſſon <hi>Steven</hi> had learned, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. Who prayed for his perſecutors: Lord lay not this ſin to their charge. See here if there be not the ſame mind in him as was in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> He prayed Father forgive them, for they know not what they do. So <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts the <hi>Philippians, Phil.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 5. that the ſame mind in them which was in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might largely inſiſt upon this, but this may ſuffice. Onely carry this along with you, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. He that ſaith he abideth in <hi>Chriſt</hi> ought ſo to walk, even as <hi>Chriſt</hi> walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The chiefeſt thing in <hi>Chriſt</hi> imitable by us, is love to the brethren, as the ſame <hi>John</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle largely and ſweetly treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of. So much for the former part of the words. A word to the latter.</p>
            <p>My brethren, my kinſmen after the fleſh. I hope you know that <hi>Paul</hi> was a Jew,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169893:15"/>and ſo his Brother-hood comes in as he was a circumciſed perſon, therefore he cals them brethren according to the fleſh, becauſe he could not call them brethren according to Faith.</p>
            <p>I proceed to the fourth verſe, which will more fully explain the precedent words: who are <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> to whom pertained the adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the glory, and the Covenants, and the giving of the Law, and the ſervice of God, and the promiſes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Whoſe are the Fathers, and of whom as concerning the Fleſh, <hi>Chriſt</hi> came, who is over all, God bleſſed for ever, Amen. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>In theſe verſes we have a Catalogue of thoſe Priviledges which the Jews had, but loſt them by their diſobedience.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Priviledge, firſt they were <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of the ſeed of <hi>Iacob,</hi> who you know was called <hi>Iſrael,</hi> upon his prevailing with God, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 32.28. This name (<hi>Iſrael</hi>) was given him as an incouragement unto him, to believe that he ſhould be a great prevailing people with God, and alſo with men; for we ſee in the next <hi>chapt.</hi> a fruit of the promiſe, when he met with <hi>Eſau</hi> his brother, <hi>Gen.</hi> 33. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4.5. and ſo forwards.</p>
            <p>Now that this was a very high Priviledge,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169893:15"/>none will deny, as to be ſuch an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> to whom ſuch promiſes did belong, for we know that God did own the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> as his choice peculiar people, both under the Law and under the Goſpel, as concerning his high expreſſion to <hi>Nathaniel, Jo.</hi> 1.47. Behold an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> indeed in whom is no guile.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> did very well to put this in the firſt place, that they were <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> becauſe there were no promiſes made, either under the Law, or under the Goſpel, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch as are or ſhall be found in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for all others are ſaid to be ſtrangers, aliens, and without God in the World, both theſe are proved by the ſame Apoſtle into his Epiſtle <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12.13. That at that time you were without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> being aliens from the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and ſtrangers from the Covenants of promiſe, having no hope, and without God in the World.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Priviledge which the <hi>Jews</hi> were inveſted withall, was the adoption, now the Greek &amp; Latin words, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>adoptio filio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi>) do ſignifie a receiving in of ſtrangers, &amp; inveſting them with ſonſhip, as we find, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. from the 23 to the laſt, where we find as well thoſe who were ſtrangers, as thoſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169893:16"/>who were born in the houſe, were called ſons, being circumciſed, this alſo was a very high Priviledge; for therein the <hi>Iews</hi> had the ſame Priviledge as <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel: for they might receive into ſon-ſhip, whomſoever would ſubmit to that Ordinance of circumciſion, and herein they did ſignifie, or type forth, that which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> concerning <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that he ſhould be as an Enſign lifted up, unto whom all nations ſhould flow ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that in <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.5. Wherein the Apoſtle doth declare our adoption by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> for ſaith he, to redeem them that were under Law, that we might receive the adoption of ſons, to this agrees <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.23. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <p>The third Previledge is the glory, wherein we muſt enquire what the Apoſtle means by the glory: Now the <hi>Greek</hi> word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies ſplendor, Majeſty, or domminion, as <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.44. Give glory to God, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.2. the God of glory appeared to our Father <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, we ſee it was one part of the <hi>Iews</hi> glory to have the preſence of God, as in the 132 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.14. for the Lord hath choſen <hi>Sion,</hi> and loved to dwell in it, ſaying, this is my reſt for ever; here will I dwell, for I have delight therein.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:169893:16"/>The ſecond part of the <hi>Iews</hi> glory is, that they had the Laws of <hi>God</hi> communicated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, 147 <hi>Pſa.</hi> 19.20. He ſheweth his word unto <hi>Iacob</hi> his ſtatutes and his judgement unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he hath not dealt ſo with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Nation, neither have they known his judgements. Even as it is in inferiour Courts, Judges, they have ſome of the glory and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of the King, becauſe they have power given them by the King, to execute his Laws and ſtatutes in his name, which in ſo doing they do repreſent the perſon of the King. I might largely inſiſt upon theſe words, but take notice of this, that theſe Priviledges are eſſential unto a Church of God, for the Covenant, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 17. was made unto them as they were ſeparated from all the Nations in the World beſides.</p>
            <p>Neither doth God make any Covenants or promiſes, either under the Law or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, but unto a people ſeparated from the pollution of the World, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 8.16. and there God dwelleth.</p>
            <p>Theſe Priviledges belonged unto them as they were the Common wealth of Iſrael, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. So that there was an Act of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom paſt upon all that came into this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, or Corporation, which Act was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169893:17"/>circumciſion, without which they had no ſhare in this Freedom or Priviledge, for this was the door by which they were to come in.</p>
            <p>I ſhall hereafter ſhew you how this doth allude to the Goſpel-principles, and indeed which is but the ſhadow of that ſubſtance which the true Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are in the dayes of the Goſpel, I proceed to the 5. verſe.</p>
            <p>Of whom are the Fathers, and of whom concerning the fleſh, <hi>Chriſt</hi> came, who is God over all, bleſſed for ever. Amen.</p>
            <p>In which words there is declared another high Priviledge added to theſe <hi>Iews,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> came of that ſtock, I ſhall not ſpeak of the Deity of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe it hath been largely treated upon by others, but onely take notice of this, that when <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſpeak of <hi>Chriſts</hi> glory, he ſpake very highly of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo that in this verſe is declared that not onely God the Father, but <hi>Paul</hi> wiſheth it ſo to be as in this word, Amen.</p>
            <p>Now from all this which hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared from the 1. verſ. to the 5. verſ. there are theſe 3. things conſiderable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the <hi>Iews</hi> were a glorious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple above all people in the World beſides.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:169893:17"/>Secondly, that they loſt this glory.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that, for which loſſe <hi>Paul</hi> was very heavy, and ſorrowfull, yet this ſorrow was not without hope, as we may ſee in the ſucceeding verſe, as in the 6. verſe.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding it cannot be, that the word of God ſhould-take none effect, for all they are not <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which are of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> verſe 6.7.</p>
            <p>Neither are they all children, becauſe they are the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but in <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhall thy ſeed be called.</p>
            <p>In theſe words the Apoſtle begins to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort himſelf concerning <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and here in he uſeth ſeveral Arguments to raiſe up his thoughts.</p>
            <p>The firſt Argument he uſeth is this, that the adoption, Covenants, promiſes, and glory, which he before ſpake of, were not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther given and made to fleſhly <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but to ſome other, or at leaſt to them under ſome other conſideration; ſo then the Argument lies thus: If the promiſes were made with <hi>Iſrael</hi> as they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed according to the fleſh onely, that is to ſay, circumciſed perſons, then it muſt not have ceaſed to ſuch an <hi>Iſrael:</hi> But we find that it hath ceaſed unto them according to the fleſh, (as <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169893:18"/>where they came to require Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> becauſe they were of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but that were not ſufficient, therefore the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes were made to <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed by faith, which are thoſe who are of the faith of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> this is clearly proved, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28, 29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For he is not a Jew which is one outwardly, neither is that circumciſion, which is outward in the fleſh, but he is a Jew which is one inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and circumciſion is that of the heart, in the ſpirit, and not in the letter, whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God, Rom.</hi> 4.14.</p>
            <p>So the Apoſtle layes all the blame upon Iſrael, not upon God; for the word of God is become of none effect to that Iſrael, becauſe they rejected this line of faith: for the Apoſtle ſaith in v. 31.32. <hi>That Iſrael hath not attained to the law of righteouſnes, becauſe they ſought it not by faith;</hi> (that is) <hi>Iſrael</hi> looked not further then this covenant accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the fleſh, as they were circumciſed perſons; upon which ground <hi>John</hi> had ſuch an harſh diſcourſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Think not to ſay you have Abraham to your father:</hi> for that is not the right line, but you are to be the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> by faith, before you claim this badge of baptiſme, as you ſhall find the words clear; and upon this
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169893:18"/>ground moſt of <hi>Pauls</hi> diſcourſe, is to beat men off from this prop, to wit, outward priviledges, as witneſſe his whole Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> eſpecially <hi>chap.</hi> 3. the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end, <hi>For ye are all the Sons of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus, if ye be Chriſts, ver.</hi> 29. <hi>then are ye Abrahams ſeed, and heirs according to promiſe.</hi> And hence it is that <hi>Paul</hi> lays low the whole diſpenſation of the law which is called <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> equall to thoſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, as <hi>Galat.</hi> 6.15. <hi>For in Chriſt Ieſus neither circumciſion nor uncircumciſion, but a new creature:</hi> And here is the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, namely, a new creature by faith. For in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> you may remember I proved being in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> was to be in and under the ordinances or diſpenſations of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. not under the law, which is called fleſh, as <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. and by circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and uncircumciſion, is meant <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the whole world, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.3.4. largely declared, ſo that now it lies here: it is not circumciſion, (that is) all thoſe priviledges, promiſes whatſoever, avails to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God now, but faith, neither is the uncircumciſion any thing, or the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, to availe for condemnation, if thou be a new creature, as it is clear <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.26.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169893:19"/>to the end. So it is the circumciſion of the heart, which was typified by the outward circumciſion of the fleſh: and therefore the ſame perſons, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. who were of this outward circumciſion, yet were uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in heart, as <hi>ver</hi> 51. Ye are ſtiff-necked and uncircumciſed in heart and ears, becauſe they did not come under the diſpenſation of the Goſpell by faith. And to this agrees the whole current of Scripture: and if you do but read <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles to the <hi>Galatians</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> you may plainly ſee this truth, ſo that here lies the cauſe; now <hi>Paul</hi> is not ſo much grieved and ſorrowfull for the <hi>Iews,</hi> becauſe they are no longer ſuch a glorious people as formerly they were: but for the cauſe of it, that they ſhould be ſo blind, as not to ſee the intent of God in all thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, as having reference to <hi>Chriſt:</hi> for it was upon this ground that <hi>Iſrael</hi> was rejected of God, and blinded, becauſe they would not ſee <hi>Chriſt</hi> the end of the law, and that now the juſt ſhould live by belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. Then we are come thus far, That the promiſes of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. and ſeverall other places, were not made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> as he was a perſon circumciſed, but as a perſon believing, and received the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169893:19"/>ſigne of circumciſion, a ſeal of the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of faith, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.10. and ſo thoſe are his children that believe in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as witneſſe <hi>Zacheus, Salvation is come to thy houſe, in as much as thou art a child of Abraham,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.26. <hi>Ye are all the Sons of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus; for as many of you as have been baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt.</hi> And thus the Word of God is not fallen away, but the <hi>Jews: Iſrael</hi> is fallen from the Word or Promiſes of God, ſo that God did never intend that men ſhould be juſtified by fulfilling the law, but by eying <hi>Chriſt</hi> in it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. Thus I am come down again to the words: Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it cannot be that the Word of God ſhould fall away, or be of none effect: ſo that thus I conclude, that <hi>Iſrael</hi> whom <hi>Paul</hi> ſo much grieved for, and thoſe that have not obeyed the Goſpell, nor entred upon that true line of faith in <hi>Chriſt:</hi> ſo the comfort lies here, <hi>That there is yet an Iſrael of God, which are thoſe that are of a clean heart, Pſal.</hi> 72.1. <hi>Pax ſuper ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s &amp; miſericordia, &amp; ſuper Iſrael Dei, Gal.</hi> 6.16. Well then, how doth this comfort <hi>Paul</hi> concerning the <hi>Iews:</hi> That at the time when thoſe <hi>Iews</hi> ſhall believe in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they ſhall be counted
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169893:20"/>for the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, and their puniſhment ſhall be taken away, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15. <hi>When they ſhall turn to the Lord, the vale ſhall be taken away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this ſhall be: and therefore <hi>Iſrael</hi> is yet in a hopefull condition, <hi>Iſrael</hi> is not yet paſt mercy and grace, and then <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> who is now hated for their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſhall then be loved, and his adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries hated: and now we muſt underſtand, that as the <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſinned, they were not only blinded ſpiritually, but afflicted outwardly, and given up into the hand of the enemies, as ye know the whole current of the Scripture runs: Now <hi>Paul</hi> is grieved for this cordition of theirs, and chiefly the cauſe of it, their unbelief: they who were ſuch a glorious people above other nations ſhould now lie amongſt the pots, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.13. that they ſhould now be the undermoſt, who then were higheſt: they the taile, that were the head, they the laſt, which were the firſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. <hi>but in Iſaac ſhall thy ſeed be called, Gen.</hi> 21.12. that is, in that line that is moſt unlikely with men: a ſon of laughter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mocking, a ſon in <hi>Abrahams</hi> old age: God in all ages made uſe of the loweſt and weakeſt means and ways to drive
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169893:20"/>on this deſigne, becauſe he will have men to ſtoop to him in this way: it muſt not be glorious <hi>Iſrael</hi> according to the fleſh, deckt with outward circumciſion, and carnall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, but <hi>Iſrael</hi> of a clean and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed heart, in the mean way of believing in <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and hence it is that <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe comes as a Carpenter of mean parents, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and mocked of men as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was, and not like a noble learned man, or wiſe after the fleſh, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. God will make men ſtoop, let them be never ſo high, never ſo learned, never ſo wiſe after the fleſh; and why ſhould men in this age wonder, if God go the ſame way to make uſe of baſe things, fooliſh things, deſpiſed things, to confound and bring to nought the high and mighty things, as wiſdome, learning, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? Why then is it that they cry now a days, as it was in <hi>Chriſts,</hi> have any of the great and learned men believed on him? onely a few poor deſpiſed ones that know not the law. But take notice, that this ſmall chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell is that where the promiſe runs: and the <hi>Jews</hi> for not ſubmitting to this way of God, lye under blindneſſe and hardneſſe till their ſtout heart comes down as <hi>Chriſt</hi> tels them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. laſt, <hi>I will not ſee you hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169893:21"/>tell you, bleſſed be he that cometh in the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here is that treating made good, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8. unto you that are not perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or are diſobedient, <hi>The ſtone which the builders refuſed, or diſſolved, the ſame is made the head of the corner.</hi> Theſe wiſe builders who at the firſt thought the ſtone not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be laid into their glorious building, muſt return, and make it the chiefe ſtone, the corner-ſtone to direct the whole build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Oh miſerable are thoſe people that are too wiſe to build upon this ſtone, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially now after they have had this preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, namely, the <hi>Iews</hi> folly and miſtake; Men are to take <hi>Chriſts</hi> Rules, examples, and preſidents to build by, though they be counted fools by the World, it muſt be ſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.60. <hi>become fools to be wiſe;</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the <hi>Iews</hi> folly was their wiſdom, being too high for <hi>Chriſt:</hi> ſo much for the 7. verſe.</p>
            <p>Verſe 8. that is <hi>They which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the fleſh, are not the Children of God; but the Children of the promiſe are counted for the ſeed:</hi> I ſpeak little to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe words, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſpake largely to the ſame thing: In the former only take notice of this, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169893:21"/>how it runs: This verſe is as it were an explication of the former, and it is <hi>Pauls</hi> ſecond <hi>Argument</hi> to comfort himſelf, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to clear <hi>God,</hi> concerning his promiſe: there are as I ſaid before two deſignes here carried on, the chief is this, <hi>Pauls</hi> kindred for whom he ſo grieves, ſhall yet again be received and exalted, becauſe they ſhall be found of the ſeed of <hi>Iſaac.</hi> The ſecond is the manifeſtation of the cauſe of this their blindneſs or hardneſs: the firſt of theſe is the chiefeſt here intended, elſe it doth no way anſwer the former part of the Chapter: neither is it a ſutable plaiſter for ſuch a ſore; for were the ſecond the chief, that is to ſay, that <hi>God</hi> hath choſen the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> of grace in <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and rejected the <hi>Covenant,</hi> the <hi>Covenant</hi> of works, <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> therefore I ſay theſe three Chapters treat chiefly of the <hi>Jews</hi> coming in again to that glory which they had only by promiſe, but ſhall have it really afterward.</p>
            <p>I might from this ſtrong affirmation of <hi>Paul,</hi> that the Children of the fleſh are not the Children of God, prove that it is not Children of believing parents, or the like that are in the promiſe, but believers.</p>
            <p>But I hope moſt people are taken off from
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169893:22"/>this groundleſſe conceit; therefore I haſten to the main and chief thing here intended, which will lie in the third Argument from the 11.12. and 13. verſes, that is thus, <hi>viz.</hi> that though <hi>Iſrael</hi> for whom I grieve ſo, be now thus lowe, yet they ſhall be brought in again, and exalted becauſe of Gods promiſe, to wit, the elder ſhall ſerve the younger: I have Gods promiſe for it, nay, this was Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically ſpoken by God (to <hi>Rebeckah</hi>) who calls things that are not as though they were, who cannot be miſtaken: Known unto God are all his works from the creation of the World; but he hath ſaid the word, <hi>Iacob</hi> ſhall riſe and <hi>Eſau</hi> fall, therefore it muſt needs be ſo: the place Iſuppoſe is known to all <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.23. <hi>Rebeckah</hi> being with child with twins, and ſtrongly ſtrugling in her Womb, or hurting one another as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word ſignifieth, ſhe could not but be troubled at this ſtrange work: Now God by this way or in this ſpeaking to <hi>Rebeckah</hi> would comfort her concerning him whom ſhe loved (who ſhould firſt be ſuppreſt by the elder,) that yet he ſhould be chief and rule over his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, therefore he gives her this promiſe, <hi>the Elder ſhall ſerve the younger, Jacob</hi> ſhall rule <hi>Eſau:</hi> Now you know that <hi>Eſau</hi> at the firſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169893:22"/>had dominion over <hi>Jacob,</hi> as witneſſeth his calling of him Lord <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſubmitting to him when he met him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 33. This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or propheſie of <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Rebeckah,</hi> as it then comforted her, ſo alſo it here comforts <hi>Paul;</hi> and therefore he makes uſe of the ſame words: Now that we may take up the whole ſcope of the words, I ſhall lay down theſe two concluſions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that <hi>Jacobs</hi> love, nor <hi>Eſaus</hi> hatred (here ſpoken of) is not yet fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the time of <hi>Jacobs</hi> love, is the time of <hi>Eſaus</hi> hatred; for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hereof, we muſt inquire what the love and hatred here ſpoken of is; for the which I ſhall refer you to the ſeveral Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies concerning <hi>Eſan,</hi> as chiefly the whole Propheſie of <hi>Obadiah,</hi> the whole Propheſie ſpeaks of this particular, as verſe the 8. and 9. they of the Mount of <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhall be cut off by ſlaughter, and in the 21. verſe, <hi>I will judge the Mount of Eſau,</hi> and add to it the laſt verſ. where he tells us when it ſhall be, to wit, <hi>when the Kingdoms are become our Lord Chriſts,</hi> likewiſe the <hi>Prophet Malachy, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachy</hi> the 1. and the 2. <hi>He hated Eſau, and laid his Mountain and his Heritage waſte for the Dragons of the Wilderneſs;</hi> but this is not yet
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169893:23"/>made good as you ſhall know, for it is when <hi>God</hi> brings back the captivity of <hi>Sion, Pſalm</hi> 137. <hi>Remember the Children of Edom,</hi> (which is <hi>Eſau) in the day of Jeruſalem,</hi> ſo that the love of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the hatred of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> is in a viſible way of exaltation or laying low: now that this is not yet clear, if you take but the ſaid 3. Chapters together, to wit, the 9.10. &amp; 11. of the <hi>Romans,</hi> Love and hatred in <hi>God</hi> are not to be looked upon as inherent paſſions as they are in man; but we ſay <hi>God</hi> is angry when it appears by his acts and works; and thus ſometimes he is angry with, or hates <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as in the 2. of <hi>Samuel,</hi> the 24. when <hi>David</hi> numbred the People; and ſo likewiſe <hi>Eſay</hi> the 60. the 14. and 15. verſes, where he ſaith, <hi>Iſrael was ſorſaken and hated,</hi> ſo likewiſe in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Pſalm,</hi> verſe 5. where the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth the noſtrils, or the appearance of anger in the noſe, becauſe we ſhould then ſay God is angry, when we ſee the effects of it, ſo that then <hi>God</hi> hateth <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> as aforeſaid in <hi>Obadiah</hi> and <hi>Malachy,</hi> when he layeth his <hi>Mountain</hi> low, and not before, and then alſo he loveth <hi>Jacob</hi> when he acts towards him, according to <hi>Pſalm</hi> the 68. and the 13. Now that <hi>God</hi> ſhall thus deal
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169893:23"/>with <hi>Eſau,</hi> and that he hath thus dealt with <hi>Jacob:</hi> I ſhall aſſert ſome <hi>Scriptures,</hi> firſt, concerning <hi>Jacob</hi> or <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> ſpeaks largely by the <hi>Prophet Ieremy, Ier.</hi> 4.6.7. verſes, <hi>he threatned to bring a plague upon them, he threatned to lay their Land waſte, and deſtroy their Cities, waſte without Inhabitant,</hi> and this was not for nothing but for their great Rebellion, chap, 3. largely ſet out; by this you ſee how <hi>Gods</hi> love or hatred appears in his acts: ſo likewiſe chap. 5.14. and 15. verſes, and verſe 25. <hi>Your iniquities have hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred theſe things from you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have further fruits of this hatred, chap. 8.17. I will ſcatter them with an Eaſt-wind before the Enemy, I will ſhew them the back and not the face, in the day of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and ſo likewiſe verſ. 19. and many other <hi>Scriptures:</hi> Now all this while <hi>Eſau</hi> who is <hi>Iacobs</hi> perſecutor, is ſaved in a ſence, becauſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> is given into his hands; for this love and hatred appears in outward Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and ſubmiſſion; and this is that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and love here ſpoken of in the Text, to wit, the making of the one great, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſmall: the major ſhall ſerve the minor; thus you ſee in ſome part the propoſition cleared. For the underſtanding what love &amp;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169893:24"/>hatred is here meant, and the time of it; For the ſecond propoſition, to wit, that the time of <hi>Iacobs</hi> love is the time of <hi>Eſaus</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, muſt needs be true; for all the world being perſecutors, or perſecuted, <hi>Iacobs</hi> or <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau's,</hi> the one being up, the other muſt needs be down: to this agrees the whole current of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and a pregnant place is <hi>Pſalm</hi> the 60. which is to this very thing in hand, concerning <hi>Eſau,</hi> under the name of <hi>Edom,</hi> where the <hi>Prophet</hi> mixeth his diſcourſe betwixt them both, as in the firſt verſe, where <hi>God</hi> is angry with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſcatters them. In the laſt verſe he threatneth to deſtroy both his and <hi>Iſraels</hi> enemies: and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 39. the whole Chapter being to this very thing in hand; ſo likewiſe <hi>Pſalm</hi> 68. at the firſt verſe, and the whole <hi>Pſalm</hi> likewiſe is eminent to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>So that is an undeniable truth, that the <hi>loving of Iacob, is the hating of Eſau,</hi> that is, <hi>the making of Iacob great, muſt be the making of Eſau ſmall;</hi> I might ſpeak much to this, but I muſt haſten. I thus conclude, that <hi>God</hi> did prophetically ſpeak unto <hi>Rebeckah,</hi> that though <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhould firſt be ſmall, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed (as you know he was,) yet afterwards at his imbracing <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> he ſhould be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169893:24"/>great and honourable: and ſo I proceed to the 14. verſe, What ſhall we ſay then? is there unrighteouſneſs with <hi>God? God</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid. Theſe words depend upon the former: the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> argues thus, men are very apt to think that <hi>God</hi> is unrighteous when he comes to render vengeance upon them, for perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his people: theſe enemies are as a rod in <hi>Gods</hi> hand, that muſt be thrown into the fire, when it ſhall be ſaid as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eſay</hi> 40.2. ſhe hath received double at the hand of the <hi>Lord,</hi> for all her tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, which is the time, which the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> now points at; that men I ſay are very apt to think that <hi>God</hi> is not righteous in his rendring a recompence to his enemies, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in their pleading with him, as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.43.44. <hi>When ſaw we thee hungry? &amp;c.</hi> but the ſecond part of the words is the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>God</hi> forbid: the ſumme of which words is this, that <hi>God</hi> ſhall appear moſt juſt and righteous in his hatred of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and love of <hi>Jacob:</hi> this is cleared expreſly by <hi>Paul, Rom:</hi> 2.4.6. <hi>for it is a rightcous thing with God, to render tribulation to them that trouble you:</hi> it is an equal and righteous thing, that as <hi>Eſau</hi> (and in him all the perſecutors and oppreſſors of the people of <hi>God</hi>) have had
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169893:25"/>their time, not only to perſecute, but to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the fatneſs of the earth; ſo <hi>Jacob</hi> who hath been ſmall ſhall alſo have his time (as it is intimated by <hi>Chriſt, Luke</hi> 16.25. concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Lazarus</hi>) ſhall have their time to enjoy the earth.</p>
            <p>I mean to reign with <hi>Chriſt</hi> on earth, herein is the righteouſneſs of <hi>God</hi> ſeen very much, and this is cleared by ſeveral <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,</hi> as <hi>Math.</hi> the 5. and the 5. <hi>The meek ſhall inherit the Earth,</hi> ſee <hi>Math.</hi> 19.28.29. <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.10. and <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 49.14. <hi>The juſt ſhall have dominion ever them in the morning.</hi> But it is objected, that this love and hatred was before they were born, verſe 11. for ere the Children were born, and when they had done neither good nor evil, that the purpoſe of <hi>God</hi> according to the election, might ſtand not of works, but of him that calleth. For anſwer to which I ſay, the words were ſpoken by God, (that calls things that are not as though they were) before they had done good or evil; and there is no more in the words, leaving out the <hi>Parentheſis,</hi> it was ſaid unto <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beckah, the elder ſhal ſerve the younger:</hi> but for more particular anſwer, I ſay as I proved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that <hi>Gods</hi> hatred and love is known by
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169893:25"/>his external actings, which is not yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed towards either of them; for the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of <hi>Eſau Malachy</hi> the 1. and the 2. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Obadiahs</hi> propheſie, was not act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before he was born, neither was it done without reference to his works, for in <hi>Obadiah</hi> its ſaid, for thy violence againſt thy brother <hi>Jacob,</hi> &amp;c. Gods promiſes &amp; threatnings have always been conditionally from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the World. As firſt concerning <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh,</hi> God threatened to bring a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon them, they repented, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented to conſider alſo <hi>Jeremy</hi> the 18. If I ſpeak againſt a Nation to pluck up and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, if that Nation turn, I will repent of the evil which I thought to bring upon them the truth of which condition of God we ſee in <hi>Ahab,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> the 21.27, 28, 29. So alſo <hi>Luke</hi> the 13. Except they repent, they ſhall all likewiſe periſh. From whence I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that God doth always threaten and promiſe conditionally: therefore if God did threaten to hate <hi>Eſau</hi> and to love <hi>Jacob,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were born; it muſt be according to theſe rules of his proceeding, which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their deſervings: for his rule is to render to every man according to his works, <hi>Romanes</hi> the 2. Now theſe conditions of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169893:26"/>God are not always expreſſed, but implied, which cauſeth the miſtake, as in the caſe of <hi>Ninive;</hi> Fourty dayes and <hi>Ninive</hi> ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: where there is no condition expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet it muſt of neceſſity be implied, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe God had not been ſo good as his word; for he did not deſtroy them. But a place emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to this purpoſe is, the firſt of <hi>Samuel</hi> the 23. the 11.12. where <hi>David</hi> inquired of God whether <hi>Saul</hi> would come down, or whether the men of the Cittie would deliver him up? the anſwer of God was firſt, that <hi>Saul</hi> would come down. And ſecondly, that the men of the Citie would deliver him up: neither of which things came to paſſe. If <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> had been of the mind of ſome men in our dayes, having a word of God, plainly ſaying that he ſhould be taken, he would not have ſtirred, but deſperately have continued in the Town till <hi>Saul</hi> had come down upon him, according as I ſaid to the words of ſome men, if they be elected they ſhall be ſaved; If not, do what they can they ſhall periſh: but would ſuch men do as <hi>David</hi> did, who fled out of the Citie and eſcaped <hi>Sauls</hi> hands, ſo let them forſake their evil wayes and turn unto God, and they ſhall be ſaved. But it is further added, that the purpoſe of God might
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169893:26"/>ſtand, that is, ſay they that God had a purpoſe to hate &amp; love in time, it is true, God did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee what the actings of theſe two would be, and except <hi>Eſau</hi> leave perſecuting of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and turn to love him, God will hate him, and when <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall turn to the Lord, God will lift them, as in the 2. of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> 3.16. when they ſhall look upon the braſen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, they ſhall be healed. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the 39. the 27.28. and 29. Gods foreſeeing that men will do good or evil, doth not give them power to act either; for did his fore-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of mens doing good give them power to act God-like, then his fore-ſight of wicked mens doing evil muſt alſo give them power to act wickedly, and ſo become the Author of ſin, which he is not: as <hi>James</hi> the firſt and the 13. <hi>Galatians</hi> the 5. and the 8. But you will ſay, that God hath power to hinder men from ſinning and therefore it lieth upon him. I anſwer, where hath God made any promiſe that he will hinder men from evil, or put them forward to good, but as Perſons ſhall imbrace his word, and by his working unto their reaſons and underſtanding? ſo <hi>Luke</hi> 14. the gueſts are invited, not forced: he doth not ſend a Troop of Horſe to bring them in by force whether they will or no, but he ſends
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169893:27"/>them word all things are ready, and this is likely to work upon their affections and to provoke them to come; for if God did put forth this kinde of power, he might cauſe a horſe or any other bruite beaſt as well as man: but the way that God takes with ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal creatures, men and women; is to woe and intreat and beſeech them to be reconciled: as in the 2. of the <hi>Corint.</hi> the 5. <hi>Eſay</hi> the 55. the 6. and 7. from all this we gather that Gods Prophetical ſpeech to <hi>Rebecca</hi> did not cauſe <hi>Eſau</hi> to be wicked or <hi>Iacob</hi> to be God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. And ſo much for the objection. And the 14. <hi>vers; vers</hi> the 15. for he ſaid to <hi>Moſes,</hi> I will have mercy on whom I will have mercy, and will have compaſſion on whom I will have compaſſion. Theſe words were the words of God to Moſes, <hi>Exodus</hi> the 33. and the 19. where <hi>Moſes</hi> deſired to ſee Gods glory, he would not be ſatisfied with a little of the back-parts; but he would ſee his face, but God doth as much as tell him, none can ſee his face, but as he is in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> that rock. Now the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here makes uſe of this promiſe of God there made to him and to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſo the words are a reaſon of the former; he argues thus <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt be loved, and mercy muſt be ſhewed unto them,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169893:27"/>why? becauſe God promiſed ſo to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and he cannot lie; ſo that this is another ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to comfort <hi>Paul</hi> concerning his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred according to the fleſh, not onely that promiſe made to <hi>Rebecca,</hi> but alſo this which was made to <hi>Moſes.</hi> But it will be objected: Gods ſupream power, is here the cauſe, and nothing in man, for it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that ſheweth mercy. For anſwer to this, I ſay, is not ſaid, it is not in him that willeth, nor in him that runneth, but that it is not of him that willeth, &amp;c. that is, it is not of or from him that willeth or runneth to procure a way of Salvation: for both <hi>Jews</hi> and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles which are here termed willers and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, are both uncapable of doing ſuch a thing; for they had both ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God, <hi>Romanes</hi> the 3. and the 23. Therefore mercy and grace, muſt needs be the gift of God, <hi>Epheſians</hi> the 2. and the 8. where Grace is called the gift of God, which gift is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, John</hi> the 4. So that it may well be ſaid, it is not of him that runneth, but of God that ſheweth mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>Hoſea</hi> the 13. and the 9. O Iſrael thou haſt deſtroyed thy ſelf, but in me is thy help. So that the caſe lies here, <hi>Paul</hi> is very ſad for
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169893:28"/>a company of condemned creatures in the beginning of the Chapter, but he is a little comforted, that the finds or hears that the King whom they have been traitors to, hath given out, that all and every one of theſe ſhall be ſaved, if they will but own him for King, which is a ſmall thing. Now the caſe of this pardon cannot ariſe from the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture condemned, but out of the Kings meer mercy. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> grieves for a company of men his kindred that are ſtung with fiery Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, but he is a little comforted in that there is a brazen Serpent ſet up to heal them if they will but look, and there is but a look required, and if they periſh it is becauſe they will not look upon the brazen Serpent; and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in alluſion to this, calleth: look unto me, and be ye ſaved all the ends of the earth. So that now there is hopes for <hi>Paul</hi> and them in this thing, becauſe willing and running is not now the way of Salvation, but looking and believing in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> it is onely now as coming to a wedding where there is all delightes, and therefore God had mercy on them that fell under the diſpenſation of the Law. But now how ſhall we eſcape if we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect ſo great Salvation? there remains now no more ſacrifice for ſin, but a fearfull look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169893:28"/>for of Judgement. And ſo much for the 16. <hi>verſ.</hi> the 17. For the Scripture ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> even for this ſame purpoſe have I raiſed thee up that I might ſhew my power in thee, and that my name might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared throughout all the earth. The words are the words of God to <hi>Pharaoh, Exodus</hi> the 9. and the 16. For the word here uſed raiſed thee up, or made thee to ſtand, the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſometimes ſignifies a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from the dead, and ſometimes a reſurrection from ſome deep extremity; ſee how God had thus raiſed up <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> how often had <hi>Pharaoh</hi> been very low by thoſe plagues which were upon him, yet God did ſtill raiſe him up and deliver him, and gave him as it were a new life, there was never any that we read of, that had more eminent mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies from God then this man had; nine ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times we know God raiſed him up from the gates of death at his deſire, by the means of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> though it were ſuch a great ſin, and evil he lay under; as firſt, the perſecuting the peculiar people of God; and ſecondly his deſpiſing and vilifying of God himſelf, ſaying, what is the Lord, that I ſhould obey him? was there ever any that abuſed deliverances more then this man did?
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169893:29"/>But let us a little examine the cauſe, becauſe he ſaith, for this cauſe; the cauſe was partly in reference to himſelf, and partly in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> Firſt in reference to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf two wayes, as is expreſſed in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words. Firſt to ſhew his patience, and ſecondly his power; his patience in forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bearing ſo many abuſes as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> offered to him and his people, as in <hi>verſ.</hi> the 22. Where both theſe particulars are proved, what if God willing to ſhew his long ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, indured with much patience the veſſels of wrath, &amp;c. Secondly, to ſhew his power, that he could take off ſuch a ſtout Enemy in the height of his rebellion &amp; perſecution, and that he did not onely to deliver and for the comfort of Iſrael then, but for the comfort of his people in ſucceeding ages, which is the very cauſe and ground that it is here cited in this Chapter; the proceedings of God upon <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that as; their God delivered <hi>Iſrael</hi> from ſo potent an Enemy, he will alſo at laſt deliver <hi>Iſrael</hi> from all the <hi>Edemites, Moabites,</hi> and <hi>Amorites,</hi> their Enemies. God will wound the head of his Enemies, and the hairy ſcalp of theſe that go on in their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, as he did unto <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> and let men make this conſtruction of all Gods deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169893:29"/>to conſider of the patience and power that God holds forth unto them; for Gods raiſing up of perſons gives them power to amend their lives, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> might and ought to have done. But the ſecond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, why God made his power appear unto <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> was in reference to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who elſe muſt have been ſwallowed up; and this proves the former Propoſition more firmly. That the time of <hi>Jacobs</hi> love muſt be the time of <hi>Eſaus</hi> hatred, for the deliverance of <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt of neceſſity be the deſtruction of <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> ſo that now <hi>Paul</hi> argues thus to comfort himſelf; God that did ſo much for <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, in delivering them from <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh;</hi> will do as much or more, in delivering them from their perſecutors, <hi>Eſau</hi> and the like. This is plainly proved by ſeveral places of Scripture, as in <hi>Eſay</hi> the 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> the 24.25. and 26. Where he deſcribes the manner of Gods proceeding, in the ſecond place to be according to that of <hi>Egypt, Eſay</hi> the 11.16. <hi>Eſay</hi> the 34. from the fifth verſe to the end; and this deliverance of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by or from themſelves, but it proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the breaſt of God himſelf, for he looked down upon <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> cruel dealing with them, and he wrought their deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169893:30"/>onely they were to do what he bid them, to go when he bid them go, and to ſtand when he bid them ſtand; and ſo muſt we or they: in the ſecond Salvation by <hi>Chriſt</hi> the mercy is free, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is free, but we muſt do as <hi>Chriſt</hi> bids us, we muſt hearken to the voice of this <hi>Prophet</hi> in whatſoever he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto us, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.37. and as it was then to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they were to hearken unto <hi>Moſes</hi> that <hi>Prophet,</hi> they were to go on when he bid them, and to ſtand ſtill when he bid them, ſo likewiſe it is now; ſo that therefore we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude thus that mercy and pardon is free, it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth: yet man muſt receive it, or elſe he ſhall be never the better: for ſo now I proceed to <hi>verſ.</hi> the 18. Therefore he will have mercy on whom he will, and whom he will he hardeneth. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> is now about to deſcribe God as a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Majeſty that hath power to puniſh or acquit; theſe words are woefully abuſed. Some gather from theſe words, that God hardens and ſhews mercy by his royal prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative onely, without reference to mans works or deſervings, yet at the ſame time the ſame perſons deny an earthly King to uſe ſuch a power, but call him a Tyrant
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169893:30"/>that doth rule by his will and prerogative and not by his Law declared; but the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> herein ſhewing the will and power of God, doth not intimate unto us, that he will quit the guilty, or condemn the innocent; but in a way of Juſtice and Equity, according to his declared Law and will, <hi>Rom.</hi> the 2. and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other places, where he declareth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward every man according to his works, and this he hath power to do, namely if men break his Laws to puniſh them, and if men obey him to reward them; Gods will here ſpoken of his his word, part of which will is <hi>John</hi> the 6. and the 40. This is the will of him that ſent me, that he that ſeeth the Son and believeth in him, ſhould have life; and the ſecond part of his will is, <hi>Mark</hi> the 6. and 16. He that will not believe, ſhall be damned. God will go by this will, and it being not obſerved, he hath this power to execute his Laws to the uttermoſt. But here I ſhall meet with a great objection, God hardens whom he will, and ſo he har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> for his will or pleaſure, to which I anſwer, that as hardneſſe and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is a ſin, ſo God hath no hand in it, but onely as it is a puniſhment of ſin, ſo he hath a hand in it, and ſo he hardned <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:169893:31"/>and ſo he blinded the <hi>Jews.</hi> But for a more particular anſwer; let us a little conſider what way and means God took to harden <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart. It is by no other means then by mercies and deliverances, for all the while the judgements were upon him, we find a ſoftneſſe in his heart; but it was upon the removing and taking off the plague (which was an Act of grace and mercy) that <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> contracts this hardneſſe upon himſelf. Now that this way was a juſt ground from God to harden <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart, let all men judge for it is the ſame way and courſe that both God and man takes to ſoften, and we know by experience that by this means ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hearts have been ſoftned, as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the 16.63.</p>
            <p>It was that that ſoftened <hi>Saul,</hi> when <hi>David</hi> ſhewed him mercy in cutting off the lap of his Garment onely, when he might have ſlain him, but this hardneſs of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart is no other ways to be attributed to God, then the ſtinck of a dunghil to the Sun, or the hardening of a clay-Wall, which we know falls out accidentally, not intentionally; and thus God provoked <hi>David</hi> to number the people, which in one place is attributed to God, and in another place to Satan;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169893:31"/>which was true on both ſides: for firſt, as he had life and motion and heat, that was frow God, but as he ſupplied this life, motion and heate, to triumph in the arme of fleſh; this was from Satan: and thus God is the authour of all the great tranſactions of the Sons of men; and thus he was the cauſe of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, at the firſt, as <hi>Adam</hi> pleadeth: <hi>The woman which thou gaveſt me, &amp;c.</hi> As much as if he ſhould have ſaid; if thou had'ſt not given me a woman to have given me the fruit, I had not committed this ſin; So if God did not uphold the lives of men, they could not ſin: but it is a very unworthy application of the mercies of God. It was the miſapplying, and miſ-improving the mercies and deliverances of God, that did neceſſarily occaſion that hardneſs to grow upon <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart; for if he were not ſoftened, he muſt needs be hardened: for Gods Word returns not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and void, <hi>Eſay</hi> 55.10.11. and in this it is like unto the Sun. But you may object, that as a judgement and puniſhment, God doth harden and blind as you ſay; therefore let us ſee what kind of hardening that is?</p>
            <p>For anſwer to which, I ſhall refer you to thoſe ſeveral Scriptures which ſpeak of this thing, as <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Becauſe I have called, &amp;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169893:32"/>ye have refuſed; ye ſhall call, &amp; I will not hear.</hi> Wherefore we may obſerve Gods part, and mans part what they were. So likewiſe, <hi>Acts</hi> the 28.26. <hi>Go ſay unto this People, hearing, ye ſhall heare, and not underſtand.</hi> The ground or reaſon is from themſelves, as in the next <hi>verſe,</hi> 27. <hi>The heart of this People is waxed fat, their eyer have they cloſed, leaſt they ſhould ſee with their eyes, and underſtand with their hearts, and be ſaved.</hi> Thus God likewiſe dealt with the Jewes, <hi>Luk,</hi> 19.42. <hi>Now they are hid from thine eyes.</hi> Thus God puniſheth ſin with ſin, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.27. <hi>Add iniquity to their iniquity.</hi> And this he hath power to do, to all thoſe that deſerve it, as the Apoſtle, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans the</hi> 2. largely declareth. Here then is the ſcope of the words, <hi>Paul</hi> is comforted concerning <hi>Iſrael</hi> again, becauſe he finds God to be righteous &amp; juſt, and alſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to deliver <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and puniſh their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: he uſeth this as an argument to ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh his heart, concerning his kindred, the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that thoſe <hi>dry bones</hi> ſhould live; that <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the whole <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, ſhall be at laſt ſet free from the perſecuting Lord <hi>Eſau,</hi> to injoy that promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. <hi>The elder ſhall ſerve the younger Iacobs</hi> enemies ſhall be ſubdued. Let us then with <hi>Paul,</hi> incourage
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169893:32"/>our ſelves, it will be ere long made good, and let us not queſtion how this can be, that theſe dry bones can live; but looke upon the power of God, who can ſhew mercy on whom he will, and whom he will, harden and deſtroy, <hi>verſe</hi> the 19. <hi>Thou wilt ſay then unto me, who hath reſiſted his will? why doth he yet complain?</hi> In the words we muſt inquire what he meaneth by this word <hi>complain.</hi> The <hi>Greek</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hath ſeveral acceptions in Scripture, <hi>Mark.</hi> 7. and the 2. <hi>They complained,</hi> or <hi>found fault.</hi> So <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.13 it is tranſlated <hi>quarrel,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23. It is tranſlated, <hi>blame.</hi> So that put theſe together, and it is thus much. <hi>A contentious complaining to pick, a quarrel,</hi> and that is, a man complains or quarrels againſt God. This appears, <hi>Lamen.</hi> 3.29. <hi>why doth living man complain? man ſuffers for his ſin;</hi> So that this it is, notwithſtanding Gods equal dealing with man, yet ſome will not be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but will reply againſt God, as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>verſe,</hi> the 14. that God is not ſo righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in his ways, therefore God pleads with <hi>Iſrael, Ezekiel</hi> 18.25. <hi>Yet ye ſay, the way of the Lord is not equal,</hi> though God dealt as exactly as he tels them that they could deſire no juſter dealing, yet they are not contented,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169893:33"/>he appealeth to all men, if this be not equal dealing, that if a righteous man, turn from his <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> he ſhall die, and if a wicked man turne from his <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> he ſhall live and not die; yet they are not ſatisfied, <hi>verſe</hi> 29. <hi>they ſay his way is not equal,</hi> So here one might aske <hi>Paul,</hi> to what end doth man complain of Gods dealing to men, their folly appears in complaining? the reaſon is given, becauſe <hi>none hath reſiſted his will;</hi> that is, when God commeth down to render ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon his enemies, and to exalt his people, none then ſhall be able to reſiſt; ſo that is a further comfort to <hi>Paul</hi> concerning <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that God comes irreſiſtibly to deliver them, as you may ſee more largely if you conſider ſome <hi>Scriptures,</hi> as <hi>Eſay.</hi> 14. the 3.4.5.6. where he ſpeaks of the thing in hand <hi>verſe</hi> the 6. <hi>He ſmote the people in his wrath, and none hindred.</hi> So <hi>Eſay,</hi> 31.13. <hi>I will work, and none ſhall let.</hi> And to clear up this irreſiſtibleneſs in God, (when he comes to recompence his enemies,) he adds the follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing verſe, <hi>ver.</hi> the 20. <hi>Nay but O man, who art thou, that replieſt againſt God? ſhall the thing formed ſay to him that formed it, why haſt thou made me thus? ver.</hi> 21. <hi>hath not the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter power over the Clay, of the ſame lump, to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169893:33"/>make one veſſel unto honour, and another to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe verſes as I have ſaid before, the Apoſtle doth undeniably prove this unreſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able power of God, in that he renders God as the <hi>Potter,</hi> and man as the <hi>Clay,</hi> which is expreſſed alſo, <hi>Eſay,</hi> 64.8. For the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of theſe words, we muſt conſider whether the making of Veſſels of honour and diſhonour, here ſpoken of, hath reference to the firſt Creation or no. Secondly, how it comes to paſſe that men are made Veſſels of honour and diſhonour. Thirdly, why he here addeth theſe words, <hi>Of the ſame lump.</hi> Fourthly, what he meaneth by veſſels of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and diſhonour, and how we ſhall be able to ſay how ſuch a perſon, or ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are veſſels of honour, or diſhonour. I ſhall by other Scripturs indeavour to clear theſe particulars. For the firſt, whether this making of Veſſels of honour, and diſhon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath reference to the Creation?</p>
            <p>I anſwer no, in no wiſe? for if theſe veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels be onely of man-kind, as all men acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; then God made but one of theſe veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, namely <hi>Adam,</hi> who was a Veſſel of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and for the whole <hi>Creation,</hi> God takes off this aſſertion, for he juſtifieth them to be
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169893:34"/>xceeding good: and ſo <hi>Solomon</hi> in <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes</hi> ſaith, <hi>God made man upright.</hi> Therefore I conclude, that God at the firſt made man a Veſſel of honour fit for the Maſters uſe: man is called a <hi>Veſſel,</hi> becauſe he is to containe ſome thing which the Maſter is to put into him, and he is honourable, ſo long as that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor remains in him, but when he leaketh or that liquor runneth out, then he becomes a diſhonourable <hi>Veſſ</hi> Secondly, neither hath it reference to what man was after <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> fall, it is true <hi>Adam</hi> became a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Veſſel</hi> by diſobeying God, but he was not thus a <hi>Veſſel</hi> of Gods making but of his own; for God created him honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as I proved before.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing to be inquired into is, how it cometh to paſſe, or at what time, man becomes a <hi>Veſſel</hi> of diſhonour? I anſwer, when men be diſobedient to God and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> then they become <hi>Veſſels</hi> of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, for this conſider the 18. of <hi>Iere.</hi> is plain to this purpoſe, from the 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> to the 17. In which Scripture we find, that God intended <hi>Iſael</hi> an honourable <hi>Veſſel</hi> till they broke in his hand; God in this declares himſelf after the manner of men, we know the Potter doth not make a <hi>Veſſel</hi> with an
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169893:34"/>intent to break it when he hath done, but this falleth out accidentally; for want of the well managing of it when it is made, neither did God make <hi>Iſrael</hi> a <hi>Veſſel</hi> wherein he might dwell intentionally to break them, and ruine them; but the caſe lay here whilſt God was in framing <hi>Iſrael</hi> for a glorious and happy condition, in that very time they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled againſt him, as is plainly expreſſed in this Chapter. A diſhonourable <hi>Veſſel</hi> in this place is a broken <hi>Veſſel;</hi> now it is not for a ſmall ſin that a Perſon or people becomes a diſhonourable <hi>Veſſel,</hi> but it is thoſe that threaten and deſperately ſay, we will walk after our own imaginations, and do every one after the ſtubbornneſſe of his own heart; here is a people fit for deſtruction, fit to be made a diſhonourable <hi>Veſſel;</hi> and now there is no other means to be uſed, this crack in ſuch an earthen <hi>Veſſel</hi> is incurable; therefore now he muſt be unchurched or excommunicated from God, therefore to ſuch a people God ſpeaketh ſadly, <hi>Eſay</hi> the 1.24. Notwithſtanding in the 14. <hi>verſ.</hi> he had promiſed them that if they would be willing and obedient, they ſhould eat the good things of the land, but if they were diſobedient, they ſhould be deſtroyed, for
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169893:35"/>the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it; God will ſpue ſuch a people out of his mouth; here is a <hi>Veſſel</hi> of diſhonour when God will no longer communicate himſelf unto him as a <hi>Veſſel</hi> for his uſe; therefore let us not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake God: it is for the higheſt and greateſt ſin that can be, to be a <hi>Veſſel</hi> of diſhonour under the Goſpel, it's to be excommunicate from the offices and fellowſhip of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, according to that in the firſt of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> 16. and the laſt, If any man love not the Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> let him be <hi>Anathema, Maranatha;</hi> this was the puniſhment of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God excommunicateth them, taketh away his preſence and his Laws from them, and delivereth them unto Satan, an adverſary; as the fornicator was to be in the firſt of the <hi>Corinth.</hi> the 5. But you have a more plain place to prove that an excommunicated Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is a diſhonourable <hi>Veſſel,</hi> as in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Timothy</hi> the ſecond and 21. If a man purge himſelf from theſe he ſhall be a <hi>Veſſel</hi> of honour fit for his maſters uſe. If the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton ſhould be asked from what he ſhould purge himſelf? it is anſwered from the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Himeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> who were excommunicate, as we may gather from the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169893:35"/>firſt of <hi>Timothy,</hi> the firſt for denying the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, ſo that from hence we gather thus much, that the imbracing their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was the ready way to be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and ſo to become diſhonourable <hi>Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> and the cleanſing or keeping a man pure from thoſe Doctrines was the ready way to be made or continued <hi>Veſſels</hi> of honour; ſo that we ſee the cauſe of mens being <hi>Veſſels</hi> of diſhonour, is their high diſobedience, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and blaſphemy againſt God, when men do as it were by theſe means break in Gods hand; when God is in making a Perſon honourable, and he doth not walk ſuitable to it, then it is that God deſigns him to be a <hi>Veſſel</hi> of diſhonour. Thirdly, why it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the ſame lump; to ſhew that it is not nearneſſe of relation that ſhall excuſe or exempt men from puniſhment, though they be of the ſame lump of the ſame fleſh and bloud, <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> you know were of the ſame lump, not onely children of one Mother, but brought forth at one birth, they were twins, yet God hateth the one and loveth the other, as is declared <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachy</hi> the 1. and the 2. Is not <hi>Eſau Jacobs</hi> brother? ſaith God, yet have I hated <hi>Eſau,</hi> and laid his mountain waſte; ſo that it ſhall
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169893:36"/>be no advantage to <hi>Eſau</hi> in the day of Gods wrath to plead that he is <hi>Jacobs</hi> own bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this <hi>Chriſt</hi> tells the <hi>Jews, John</hi> 8. and 37. I know that ye are <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, ſaith <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but you ſeek to kill me; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſhould not abide in the houſe, they muſt not be <hi>Veſſels</hi> of honour in his houſe, <hi>verſ.</hi> the 35. So likewiſe in <hi>Matth.</hi> the 3. <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſheweth that it is not near re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation that can ſerve the turn, though they be <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed. So likewiſe <hi>Matth.</hi> the 24.40. Two woman ſhall be grinding at the Mill, one ſhall be taken, and the other left.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, what he meaneth by, or when a perſon or people may be ſaid to be a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Veſſel.</hi> This was partly cleared in the 2. particular, but you ſhall a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee this cleared: when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up into the hand of her Enemies, then ſhe was a diſhonourable <hi>Veſſel;</hi> when ſhe lieth amongſt the pots, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.13. When ſhe is caſt aſide, as men commonly caſt aſide a broke pitcher as a <hi>Veſſel</hi> of no uſe or honour; and ſhe is again received to be a <hi>Veſſel</hi> of honour, when ſhe believeth in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſhe ſhall again be imployed for the Maſters uſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.23. If they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169893:36"/>abide not ſtill in unbelief, they ſhall be graft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in: ſo that we underſtand thus much, that God doth not make men <hi>Veſſels</hi> of honour and of diſhonour, but upon juſt ground and ſufficient cauſes. I might prove this by ſeveral Scriptures, but I ſhall onely cite two; <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.26. For this cauſe God gave them up to uncleanneſſe, the 2. of the <hi>Theſſ.</hi> the 2. and 11. For this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions; there is a juſt cauſe why God dealeth ſo with men, and God doth ſo far condeſcend as to give man an account of it, therefore he doth not rule by his will or prerogative as ſome men ſay. Let us then a little inquire into the cauſe why <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhall be thus hated, or made a diſhonourable <hi>Veſſel. Eſau</hi> is now an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Veſſel,</hi> as God maketh uſe of him to correct <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but when <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be ſufficiently corrected by him, he is to be thrown into the fire, becauſe he hath corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not as being in Gods hand, but as ſatisfying his corrupt heart and cruel hands, <hi>Obadiah</hi> the 10. For thy cruelties to thy brother <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhame ſhall cover thee. The cauſe of <hi>Eſaus</hi> being made a <hi>Veſſel</hi> of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonour, is granted by the Prophet <hi>Amos, Amos</hi> the 1. The whole chapter ſpeaks of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169893:37"/>this thing, but eſpecially <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. he hath not remembred the brotherly Covenant, but pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued him with the ſword, and caſt off all pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as <hi>verſ.</hi> the 11. Yet the cauſe of this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Jacob</hi> or <hi>Iſrael</hi> is juſt too <hi>Mich.</hi> 1.5. For the wickedneſſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> is all this come upon them; ſee likewiſe <hi>Michael</hi> the 6. Yet God had not given <hi>Iſrael</hi> any ſuch cauſe as he pleadeth with them to be ſo rebellious, <hi>verſ.</hi> the 3. O my people what have I done unto thee? or wherein have I wearied thee? teſtify againſt me. The Lord appealleth unto man in all his proceedings, that if man doth ſee, or Judge, that God hath not in any thing dealt juſtly, or equally, let him ſpeak, or plead, for he is not afraid that men ſhould dive or ſearch into his proceedings in reference to man as ſome men will affirm; therefore <hi>Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels</hi> of honour and diſhonour are of Gods making for juſt cauſe and grounds, given by themſelves and no otherways, <hi>verſ.</hi> the 22. What if God willing to ſhew his wrath and to make his power known endured with much long-ſuffering, the <hi>Veſſels</hi> of wrath fitted to deſtruction? I ſhall be very brief in the following diſcourſe. The words are a further vindication of God, that he doth not (as ſome ſay) make <hi>Veſſels</hi> of honour and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169893:37"/>diſhonour, without reference to their works, nay, he is ſo far from that that after they deſerve to be made <hi>Veſſels</hi> of diſhonour, yet he waits a long time upon them; and uſeth all means to reclaim them, he ſuffereth with long patience, the <hi>Veſſels</hi> fitted or made up for deſtruction, this the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel, Ezekiel</hi> the 33.11. ſpeaketh largely to, why will ye die. O houſe of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> and how ſhall I give thee up, (ſaith God to <hi>Iſrael,</hi>) it grieves him to do it; and therefore it is called his ſtrange work, executing of judgement of this long-ſuffering and patience of God, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. And ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that the long-ſuffering of God is for Salvation: to this agreeth the firſt of <hi>Tim.</hi> the 4.2, and the 4. and remains the 2. and the 4. Which is very pregnant to this purpoſe, but this is not the thing which is ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted, but the queſtion is, whether this fitting or or making up to deſtruction, be not Gods appointing and ordaining men to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction from eternity? becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> the 1. the 2. and the 8. He ſpeaks of ſome that were diſobedient whereunto they were appointed, and <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks of ſome that were of ould ordained to this condemnation: for that of <hi>Peter</hi> the words run thus according to the Greek, being not perſwaded, becauſe they
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169893:38"/>were agreed or reſolved <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſame word is uſed, <hi>Joh.</hi> the 9. and the 22. The Jews had agreed or ordained, that if any ſhould confeſſe <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they ſhall be caſt out of the <hi>Synagogue:</hi> for the 2. place, <hi>Jude</hi> the 4. of old ordained, the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>praeſeripti,</hi> ordained by writing: in the Law, and who were them, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men, turning the grace of God into wantonneſſe; deſtruction muſt be to the workers of iniquity. And the curſe of the Lord are in the houſe of the wicked, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs</hi> the 3. and the 33. But he bleſſeth the habitation of the juſt. The wiſe ſhall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit love, but ſhame ſhall be the portion of fools. So it is fitting for deſtruction is one mans part, it is he that muſt fill up his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaks to the <hi>Jews, Matth.</hi> the 23. Fill ye up the meaſure of your Fathers, and then wrath muſt come upon them to the uttermoſt, without remedy when they are thus filled up they are fit for deſtruction; ſo was <hi>Pharaoh</hi> fitted for deſtruction by his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hardening his heart, the firſt of <hi>Samuel</hi> the 6. and the 6. Yet upon ſuch a perſon or people God waits, <hi>Romanes</hi> the 10. and the laſt <hi>verſ.</hi> All the day long have I ſtretched out my hand to a gain-ſaying, and rebellious
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169893:38"/>people. So God waits all the day long upon wicked men, to ſee whether they will return. Thus you ſee how theſe words agree with the former. Man is very apt to reply againſt God, becauſe he doth not preſently make his power appear in puniſhing the wicked, and rewarding the Godly, according to that which <hi>Solomon</hi> in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> ſpeaks, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe judgement is not ſpeedily executed, therefore the hearts of the Sons of men are ſet in them to do wickedly. This is the uſe that moſt men make of Gods long-ſuffering and forbearance. So <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of mockers walking after their own luſts: the reaſon is becauſe all things continue as they were the people of God alſo are very apt to repine and mourn that God doth not preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them, <hi>Hebrews</hi> the 10. Ye have need of patience, ſaith the Author, that when ye have done the will of God, you ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the promiſes. But here in the words you have the cauſe why he doth thus wait, that his blow might be the heavyer unto all the <hi>Pharaohs</hi> in the World, and that his riches of grace might appear the more eminently unto the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God; which brings us to the 23. <hi>verſ.</hi> the 23. <hi>ver.</hi> And that he might make known the riches of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169893:39"/>on the <hi>Veſſels</hi> of mercy, which he had afore prepared unto glory. He hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared unto glory all thoſe that believe in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and obey him, <hi>Romanes</hi> the 2. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> the 4. and the 3. He hath ſet apart for himſelf the Godly man. The firſt of the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> the 1. and 4. They were elect of God, becauſe they became followers of <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt, as <hi>verſ.</hi> the 6. <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> the 2. the 2. and the 13. You are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen of God, through <hi>ſanctification</hi> of the Spirit and belief of the truth: ſo that if you be ſanctified and obedient, you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude you are the elect of God, Gods cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen ones, Gods Jewels, thoſe that own <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> for the foundation-ſtone to build upon: the firſt of <hi>Peter</hi> the 2. and the 7. God hath prepared glory for no other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; for no unclean thing ſhall enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Kingdom, therefore the Apoſtle ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, they muſt be ſanctified, they muſt be called, not onely on Gods part (which all men are,) but ſuch as have ſubmitted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods call. Choſen; that is, thoſe that are counted Gods choice, that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to follow him as an obedient ſpouſe; there is a great miſtake in ſuch expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as theſe: you have not choſen me,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169893:39"/>but I have choſen you; where we are to conſider <hi>Chriſt</hi> as one woing a wife, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that the 2. of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> the 5. Now we know it is not uſual for the wife to look for, or to chuſe the husband: yet there muſt be a conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or elſe it is not a match, and thus the wife chuſeth the husband above all the men in the VVorld beſides; and thus <hi>Marie</hi> was ſaid to have choſen the better part, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the firſt mover in this buſineſſe; ſo that the ſum of all is, God waiteth with long patience upon all, good and bad; <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> he waits on <hi>Eſau</hi> to ſhew the power of his wrath, and on <hi>Jacob</hi> to ſhew the riches of his mercy; and not onely ſo, but ſo, but for the Gentiles ſakes, that they may come in, the fulneſſe of them, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in the 10. and 11. <hi>verſes.</hi> The 24. <hi>ver.</hi> Even as whom he hath called not of the <hi>Jews</hi> onely, but alſo of the Gentiles. For the right underſtanding of the words, we muſt look into the Prophet <hi>Hoſea; Hoſea</hi> the 1. and the 9. and 10. And indeed the whole Chapter, where he ſpeaks both of <hi>Iſraels</hi> cutting off, and coming in; he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to take them of from their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169893:40"/>confidence that they were high in the eſteem of God, being his children of whoredom, Chapter the 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> the 4. And ſo he threatneth them as ſuch a people, yet he interlines his threatnings with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of mercy, as <hi>verſ.</hi> the 23. I will ſowe her unto me in the earth; I will have mercy upon her that had not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained mercy, &amp;c. So that when the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks of calling, he means calling by the Goſpel, offering <hi>Iſrael</hi> the means which once they abuſed and contemned, and in this appeareth his love; yet this appearance of love from God, is when they ſhall ſay, bleſſed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord, <hi>Matth.</hi> the 23. and the 39. They ſhall be glad to imbrace him whom once they rejected, the 1. of <hi>Peter</hi> the 7. and 8. So that it is to theſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ones that the promiſe runs, to thoſe that are not rebellious, as Chapter the 10. and the laſt <hi>verſ.</hi> For had God come by this power as ſome do imagine, to force men to accept him, then his power was too weak to deal with Iſrael; for he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, I have ſtretched out my hand all day long to a rebellious people; and he ſaith, what could I have done more that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169893:40"/>I have not done? as in the parable of the vine-yard; therefore there was all the power Acted on Gods ſide, but this would not do; therefore this calling here ſpoken of, is onely the invitation of the Goſpel, and thoſe that are overcome by this invitation, as to come upon <hi>Chriſts</hi> call, they are the called ones, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaks of; and upon this we are exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make our calling and Election ſure: it lies on our part when the means is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> calls we are to anſwer. The word <hi>vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abo</hi> doth imply the giving a name to a thing; it is ſo uſed in the next <hi>verſ.</hi> In the place where it was ſaid they are not my people, there they ſhall be called the children of the living God: ſo it is uſed, <hi>Epheſians</hi> the fourth and the firſt. That you walk worthy of the vocation whereunto you are called. That is, you know that you are called Chriſtians, or Saints; I exhort you, that you walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſuch a name. So that <hi>Paul</hi> here intimates that upon their return they ſhall have a new name, that is, they ſhall be called or named <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: a people. Ye are to know; they had this name before, but they loſt it by their rebellion
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169893:41"/>and diſobedience; a people that is in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to Nations or Gentiles; ſo that they were a Church for corporation, having Laws and ſtatutes to walk by, <hi>verſ.</hi> the 25. As he ſaith alſo in <hi>Oſea;</hi> I will call them my people, which were not my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and her beloved, which was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved. And it ſhall come to paſſe, that in the place where it was ſaid unto them, ye are not my people; there ſhall they be called the children of the living God. In theſe 3. verſes the 24.25. and 26. is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared ſome fruits of the long-ſuffering and patience of God towards the <hi>Veſſels</hi> of mercy, prepared unto glory; the 25. <hi>verſ.</hi> Seemeth to relate to the Gentiles, and their grafting in: but look diligently into the plaee which <hi>Paul</hi> cites, and it will appear to be undone, or unchurch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Iſrael;</hi> which were rejected for their whoredoms, and fornications, as plainly appeareth by that Propheſie. And unto that add <hi>Peter</hi> the 1. the 2. and the 10. And it makes it more plain, for <hi>Iſrael</hi> now are not a people, by reaſon they are ſcattered, and diſſolved, and in that ſence they may be called Nations, as once the Gentiles were. So that laying the <hi>Jews</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:169893:41"/>equal with the Gentiles in reſpect of being a people, was the onely way to make them capable of mercy. This appears plainly in <hi>Romans</hi> the 3. at the 25. and <hi>Romans</hi> the 11. at the 32. God hath ſhut up, or concluded all in unbelief; that he might have mercy upon all. Thus God hath hedged up their way with thorns, and ſtopped all paſſages every way, that no life or comfort can come unto it, but by believing and ſubmitting to the Goſpel, as <hi>Galathians</hi> the 3. and the 22. All are ſhut up under ſin. So that now there is no people but believers, as appeareth plainly the 1. of <hi>Peter</hi> the 2. and the 9. Ye are a peculiar people (to wit,) believers; and the <hi>Jews</hi> are not a people, becauſe they do not believe. Therefore God may well make a promiſe, to make them a people, who are not a people now. In the next verſes the Apoſtle doth (as it were) produce a Copy of <hi>Iſraels</hi> commitment; wherein is declared, firſt, the extent and depth of their miſery, ſecondly the cauſe, why it was ſo; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he directeth you to the propheſie of <hi>Eſay,</hi> Chapter the 10. Which I pray ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly read and conſider, for the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of theſe things; wherein is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared at large the extent of their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169893:42"/>with the cauſe thereof; and alſo a promiſe of their return: for the extent of the puniſhment it was ſo ſore, that a very ſmall remnant eſcaped; in-ſo-much, that it was almoſt brought to <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah's</hi> condition, wherein there were but eight per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſaved, 1. <hi>Peter</hi> the 3. and the 20. Now in the 30. and 31. verſes the Apoſtle begins to make the application of all that hath been ſaid, (to wit) that a righteous <hi>Iſrael</hi> could not be acceptable with God, but the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Gentiles. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Which ſinners we find were under the name of Gentiles; the <hi>Jews</hi> were whole, therefore they needed not the Phyſitian, they muſt be ungodly ones, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt be a Saviour to. So that he concludes thus: a people ſelf-righteous, are thoſe that ſtumble at <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and ſtumbling at him they become broken to pieces like an earthen <hi>Veſſel:</hi> And upon this <hi>Iſrael</hi> now lies amongſt the pots, caſt aſide as uſeleſſe. So that from the whole chapter we draw thus much that <hi>Paul</hi> was very much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at the <hi>Jews</hi> ſad condition, becauſe they are fallen from the word or promiſe of God. But he calleth to mind ſeveral promiſes of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169893:42"/>God concerning them, or at leaſt ſo many of them, as ſhall believe in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> We may gather thus much from what is here comprehended, that all external pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments are inflicted upon Nations, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or Perſons, as they are found in Arms or oppoſition againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed way of the Goſpel. And ſecondly, people, Nations, or Perſons, ſhall be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly exalted, as they are found friends to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and obedient Perſons to the Goſpel. I ſhall produce ſome Scriptures to prove this, and ſo conclude my diſcourſe. For this conſider <hi>Matthew</hi> the 19. from the 27. to the end. <hi>Revelations</hi> the 5. and the 10. <hi>Revelations</hi> the 20. and the 4. <hi>Luke</hi> the 12. and the 32. And a place eminent to this purpoſe is, <hi>Luke</hi> the 23. and the 43. Where as ſoon as the thief confeſſed <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> whom (all thereabouts) mocked and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed; <hi>Chriſt</hi> makes him a promiſe, that he ſhould have a ſhare with him in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. I ſay unto thee to day, thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe; which is this Kingdom. So that you ſee, the onely way to have Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and greatneſſe; is, to believe in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> though moſt in the World deſpiſe and reject him; for if we ſuffer with him we
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169893:43"/>ſhall alſo Reign with him, the 2. of <hi>Timothy</hi> the 2. and the 12. the 1. of <hi>Timothy</hi> the 4. and the 8. Godlineſſe hath the promiſes both of this life, and of that which is to come. The juſt ſhall have domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the morning of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Pſal. 49. &amp; the 7. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeek firſt the Kingdom of Heaven, and the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, &amp; all other things ſhall be added unto you.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> the 29. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>John Downame.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
